<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Edison Orellana</title>
    <description>Personal website for Edison Orellana</description>
    <link>edison.me/</link>
    <atom:link href="edison.me/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>2016-12-18 17:11:28 -0600</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>2016-12-18 17:11:28 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Arduino Powered Motorcycle Tachometer</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My motorcycle doesn’t come with an onboard tachometer, so I want to add my own. While I’m at it, why not add an entire control system? I have big dreams for my moto-computer. Some of my ideas so far:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Smart dash display&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gear indicator&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;GPS tracking system for recovery and telemetry&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Remote choke actuation + remote start (but what’s the point really?)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Control custom lighting&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Custom cyberpunkish tail lights&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rear and front dashcams on loop record&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;RFID starter&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pebble integration to buzz me when I forgot to cancel my turn signal&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gas meter + gas consumption data logger&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is certainly no shortage of ideas. Implementing all of thes ideas would be exceptionally difficult, so I’d like to start with just a tachometer and work my way up. I’ve already done extensive research on some of the circuitry I’d need. &lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>2016-06-20 07:32:18 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>edison.me/motorcycle/2016/06/20/arduino-cycle/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">edison.me/motorcycle/2016/06/20/arduino-cycle/</guid>
        
        <category>motorcycle</category>
        
        <category>arduino</category>
        
        <category>hardware</category>
        
        
        <category>motorcycle</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Estimating Leaf Cover in Costa Rica Forests using k-means Clustering</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post serves to summarize a project I did for my ESE 389: ENVIRONMENTAL &amp;amp; SUSTAINABLE FIELD EXPEDITION - COSTA RICA class. The class is described on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.earth.illinois.edu/cms/one.aspx?portalId=4186&amp;amp;pageId=107405&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; as an “8 day trip to Costa Rica over Spring Break with weekly seminars on campus during the regular semester. The course will examine environment and sustainability issues in Costa Rica. Coverage includes: rainforest ecology, land-use issues, sustainable agriculture, developing economies, and geologic features of the landscape (e.g., volcanoes; rivers).” The class culminated in a major project whose requirements necessitated that the project be related to sustainability and Costa Rica. I chose to do an assessment on the canopy cover for the different forests we visited in Costa Rica.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/edisondotme/canopy-cover/raw/master/plots/map.png&quot; alt=&quot;Costa Rica Forests&quot; title=&quot;Costa Rica Forests&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had recently learned about a technique in my GEOG 479: Programming for GIS class where one can estimate the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leaf_area_index?oldformat=true&quot;&gt;leaf area index (LAI)&lt;/a&gt; of a forest using images taken from the ground pointing straight up to the sky. The technique uses a camera with a very wide angle &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hemispherical_photography?oldformat=true&quot;&gt;hemispherical&lt;/a&gt; (fish-eye) lens whose field of view extends from horizon to opposite horizon, then processing that image to determine which parts are sky, and which parts are leaf to determine the LAI. I thought the technique was clever so I decided that I wanted to try it out myself for my project. There exists scientifically rigorous software that already exists for this technique such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.delta-t.co.uk/product/hemiview/&quot;&gt;hemiview&lt;/a&gt;, but for the sake of scientific exploration and learning, I wanted to whip up a version of my own using one of my most beloved languages, R.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;process&quot;&gt;Process&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Canopy cover assessment with hemispherical photography begins using a binarization algorithm, which just just analyzes the images and categorizes pixels as leaf or non-leaf. I had also recently conducted a workshop as part of the student organization I ran (&lt;a href=&quot;http://ugisgroup.org&quot;&gt;ugisgroup.org&lt;/a&gt;) teaching &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/K-means_clustering?oldformat=true&quot;&gt;k-means clustering&lt;/a&gt; of spatial points. I applied that workshop to the pixels in the hemispherical image to categorize the pixels into two groups: leaf and sky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a snippet of the relevant code in R:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;R
 km &amp;lt;- kmeans(as.vector(image), centers = 2)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result is something that looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/edisondotme/canopy-cover/raw/master/plots/clustered_image.png&quot; alt=&quot;Costa Rica Forests&quot; title=&quot;k-means clustered forest image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above image is the result of running the R built in kmeans clustering algorithm looking for 2 centers (leaf or sky). The algorithm seems to be very good at picking out leaf from non-leaf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t go into rigorous depth to calculate the LAI from the clustered images, though it is just a couple extra steps. Since I was only interested in comparing the relative canopy covers among the different forests, I opted to just use percent canopy cover instead of LAI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is a simple plot that compares the percent canopy cover for different forests in Costa Rica.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/edisondotme/canopy-cover/raw/master/plots/mainplot.png&quot; alt=&quot;Graph of percent leaf cover&quot; title=&quot;percent leaf cover graph&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also did a presentation on this for my class. &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1oULHJWyrmwFsGlJhjWdb8Vo2sWT9wUim4BRLgS-18zw/edit#slide=id.g13d5aff0e2_0_51&quot;&gt;Here is the link&lt;/a&gt; to the slides I used during my presentation. There is very little text on my slides because I don’t believe in putting text on powerpoint slides, but the pictures help to explain more about my project. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The code for this project can be found on my Github at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/edisondotme/canopy-cover&quot;&gt;this link&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>2016-05-10 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>edison.me/code,/gis/2016/05/10/canopy-cover/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">edison.me/code,/gis/2016/05/10/canopy-cover/</guid>
        
        <category>hemispherical photography</category>
        
        <category>machine learning</category>
        
        <category>R</category>
        
        
        <category>code,</category>
        
        <category>gis</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Contour plots on TI-Nspire</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/2pwBGJDoX-o&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>2013-06-20 07:32:18 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>edison.me/nspire/2013/06/20/countour-plots-nspire/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">edison.me/nspire/2013/06/20/countour-plots-nspire/</guid>
        
        <category>nspire</category>
        
        
        <category>nspire</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>